Guide to the SHARE records, 1968-ongoing UA.09.06.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
SHARE records
1968-ongoing.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Student Housing for Academic and Residential Experimentation
UA.09.06.0001
4.5 Linear Feet
Contains the records of SHARE (Student Housing for Academic and Residential Experimentation), a co-educational residential living group at Duke University. Types of materials include correspondence, minutes, reports, evaluations, financial materials, applications, plaques, a videotape, short writings, newsletters, literary magazines, notes, photographs, and clippings. Major subjects include residence and education, Duke University, Epworth Inn, Wilson House, Faculty Apartments, experimental living, Program II, college freshmen, and faculty advisor John M. Clum. Materials range in date from 1968 to ongoing. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The SHARE records were received as transfers in 1977, 1983, 2002, and 2009 (Accession numbers 77-203, 83-93, A2002-66, UA2009-0020, UA2014-0038).
Historical Note
SHARE (Student Housing for Academic and Residential Experimentation) was founded in 1970 as an academically elite experimental living group of 54 men and women. The integrated residence, then known as the Experimental College, was part of Duke's "New Curriculum". The "New Curriculum" recommendations of 1969 had suggested various changes in living arrangements for students on campus, including the elimination of freshmen dormitories and the establishment of a co-educational dormitory.
SHARE generally included students who were creative and possessed special talents or interests. SHARE applicants also had to demonstrate a clear sense of academic direction, and show interest in helping develop programs of the Experimental College within the first year. Students enrolled in Program II, an interdisciplinary study program, were given preference to live in the SHARE house.
The first director, overseeing the academic progress of residents, was English professor John Clum. Clum worked closely with the administration of Duke University to blend SHARE's social and academic components into a sustainable living environment. SHARE was first located in the Faculty Apartments (now Wilson House) on Duke University's East Campus. The apartment-type layout of the building allowed for men and women to live closely together while preserving privacy. SHARE participants lived in Wilson House until 1982, then in Alspaugh House from 1983 to 1984. In 1984, SHARE moved again to Epworth Inn, where it would remain until 1997. In 1997, SHARE was moved to Wilson House.
SHARE programming consisted of a variety of seminars, credit courses, meetings, film festivals, and lectures. Events included a "Use Your Appendages" Party, Anime Fest, Epworth Prom (Oil My Lizard), The Epworth Retreat, and "Twilight", a rave. Two of the most notable activities were SHARE hours and Pedagogo. SHARE hours gave members of the dorm an opportunity to tell others about their interest and experiences. Pedagogo was a series of events where members of the Duke University faculty were invited to Epworth to speak informally about issues in research and academics.
In 1995, SHARE became the first living group on campus to include members from all four undergraduate years. SHARE persisted as an alternative to conventional Duke residential life. When cited for low membership in 1997, SHARE was relocated from Epworth House to the third floor in Wilson House. As of 2003, SHARE is active at Duke University.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of SHARE, an experimental co-educational student living organization housed in Wilson House, Alspaugh House and Epworth Inn on Duke University's East Campus. Types of materials include correspondence, minutes, reports, evaluations, financial materials, applications, plaques, a videotape, short writings, newsletters, literary magazines, notes, photographs, and clippings. Materials range in date from 1968 to ongoing. Contains restricted materials.
Related Material
Alspaugh House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Association of Independent Houses records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Association of Independent Houses records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Bassett House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Brown House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Bunch of Guys records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Few Federation records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Fraternities and Sororities collection.
University Archives, Duke University.
Gilbert-Addoms Residence Hall records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Giles House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Jarvis House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Living Groups collection.
University Archives, Duke University.
Mirecourt House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Pegram House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Warwick House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
York House records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Dormitories -- North Carolina; College students -- Alcohol use -- North Carolina -- Durham; College students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Student housing -- North Carolina -- Durham; Residence and education; Duke University. Alspaugh House; Duke University. Program II; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Duke University -- Students; Clum, John M.; Duke University. Wilson House; Duke University. Student Housing for Academic and Residential Experimentation
- Correspondence (John Clum), 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- House Courses correspondence, general, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1974-1984 (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
- Community service, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Retreat, in-dorm, 1974 (Box 1)
- Conference, 1971 (Box 1)
- Film festivals, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
- Reports, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
- Subcommittee on Curriculum, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
- Curriculum, early planning materials, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- House Courses, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- House Courses, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Small-group experience surveys, 1970 (Box 1)
- General history of SHARE/Epworth/Wilson (Box 1)
- General housing: Wilson, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1970-2001 (Box 1)
- Clippings re: Epworth move, 1997 (Box 1)
- Printed material, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1980 (Box 1)
- Transcript: Interview with John Clum, 21 March 1980 (Box 1)
- "The Wilsonian or The Gnome at Home," 1975-1976 and Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1)
- Questionnaires, 1980 (sampling) (Box 1)
- Event Materials, 1970-1986 (Box 1)
- Event Materials, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
- Event Materials, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
- Event Materials, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- Event Materials, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
- Event Materials, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
- SHARE Long Sleeve T-shirts (Box 1)
- Administrative Records [RESTRICTED] (Box 2)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  This box contains administrative records that are restricted for 25 years from their date of origin. In the interim, these records can only be accessed with the permission of the office of origin and the University Archivist. Please contact the University Archives for more information.
- Council and Board, 1992-1996 (Box 2)
- Event Materials, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
- Jamaica Jam, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
- Event Materials, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
- Events, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
- Reports, 1985-1993, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
- Annual Report 1997 and Writings in Support of SHARE, 1997 (Box 2)
- House Courses 1985-1986 (Box 2)
- House Courses 1987- (Box 2)
- General- Identity Establishment/ Short Writings, 1971-1987 (Box 2)
- East Campus Residence, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
- SHARE Proposal to become a cross-sectional house, 1995 (Box 2)
- Housing Problems, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
- General Housing- Programming and Residents, 1991-1992, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Materials, n.d. (regarding SHARE) (Box 2)
- Short Writings and Miscellaneous Materials, ca 1971-ca 1974 (Box 2)
- Short Writings 1994-1995 (Box 2)
- Short Writings and Newsletters, 1996 (Box 2)
- Quotes, 1989-1990, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 2)
- Applications, 1990-1991 (questionnaires) (Box 2)
- SHARE Interview Book, n.d. (Box 2)
- Epworth Appeal, 1997 (Box 2)
- Meeting Minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
- Recruitment and Freshman Experience, 1997 (Box 2)
- Symposiums, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
- Constitution, undated (Box 2)
- SHARE History, 1997 (Box 2)
- Bi-Annual Review, 2000 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous, 1995-1999 (Box 2)
- Administrative Records [RESTRICTED] (Box 3)
- Applications, 1970-1971, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
- Applications, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
- Applications, 1974-1975 (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Wilson House Records, applications and evaluations for residence, 1977-1982 (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Applications, 1985-2001 (12 folders) (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
- Correspondence re: Epworth move, 1997 (Box 3)
- Correspondence re: Faculty-in-Residence, 1999 (Box 3)
- Constitutions, 1995, 1996 (Box 3)
- Minutes, 1990-1994 (Box 3)
- Financial, 1971-1976/1977, 1985/1986 (Box 3)
- SHARE scrapbook, 1995 (Box 3)